if i was to begin learning piano again
starting today these are some of the
most important things i would do over
the next year the next couple of years
in order to get a solid start and a good
foundation to learn it's all the stuff
that i know has lots of long-term
benefits makes learning easier and makes
you a better musician throughout the
video i'll be listing loads of topics
and things and in the description below
i've put lots of links to other videos
and resources where you can go and learn
those things let me know in the comments
below and share with everyone else what
are some of the most helpful things that
you're learning
okay so the first thing is that apart
from in the very very beginning when
you're just getting familiar with the
piano and using your fingers i would
spend the largest amount of my practice
time learning real music so learning
songs and pieces of course all the other
exercises things to do and musical
knowledge to learn is going to help you
improve and get the most out of playing
but to put it simply i think that you
can learn the most about playing music
by actually doing it out of that time i
think it's really beneficial to try and
learn a variety of music that's going to
get you using the piano in different
ways and using your hands in different
ways and really importantly some of that
music needs to be music that you love
music that you want to play that's going
to inspire you and motivate you to keep
playing i would learn some chord
accompaniments because they immediately
sound a bit more professional they help
you learn about chords in a musical way
and when the chords are played in more
simple patterns less broken up it's
easier for you to actually keep track of
what chords you're playing learn about
how chord progressions work and start to
gain a clearer picture of how music is
put together they're really good for
working on your rhythm and the
interaction between your hands and
they're fun especially if you want to
sing or make music with other people
beginner classical pieces are really
going to help you work on lots of other
areas of technique and through that
you're going to learn lots of valuable
technical skills that you can apply and
help you out in whatever else you want
to play and there's a wide variety of
techniques that you can learn so compare
something like the beginner sections of
fur release which has these broken
chords which are flowing and spread out
over a wide distance and compare that to
something else like menu ng which has
these more intricate interweaving parts
in each hand two skills that feel very
different but will both help you in lots
of areas of playing piano there's also
lots of simple beginner music in books
and on youtube that can be really
beneficial they're often shorter so you
can get through a wider variety of
things and different styles of music
sometimes beginner pieces may not always
have the most inspiring arrangements but
bear in mind it is also good to learn
some things even if it's not your first
choice if you're going to gain something
important out of learning it so you do
want to try and choose material that's
the right level of challenge for you for
your core practice because
trying to play stuff that's too out of
your league it doesn't really help you
learn as well and it can even put you
off playing when it feels too hard it's
better to build up to things but having
said that as long as you are getting
that more nutritious part of your
musical diet in make sure that you save
some time purely for fun stuff to keep
you motivated keep you enjoying music
where you can try out whatever you like
and push your boundaries
learning scales starting with some of
the majors and then some of the minors
is really a must so i would not think i
could get away with skipping this they
really are one of the backbones of music
they give you a chance to practice some
of your basic techniques at the
beginning get your hands working
together they help you learn to use your
fingers properly and really importantly
they teach you the shapes on the piano
that you need to be able to recognize
the groups of notes that we use and move
in and around of to play actual music
you don't have to learn them all at once
in the first year or so i would focus
mainly on the majors and then the minors
starting from the white notes starting
with c major first i've done a video
that gets a bit more in depth on a
helpful order to learn scales in i've
done a playlist of tutorials for all the
major scales i'll be doing more
practical videos on scales this year and
i do have some pdfs which have clear
notation and graphics and finger numbers
all clearly laid out for you and there's
links for all that stuff below
the next thing i would focus on is
getting really familiar with finding and
being able to wrap my fingers around all
the basic chords we use and their
inversion positions so starting again
from scratch i would dedicate more
specific practice time to really getting
used to these positions that we use all
the time in music when you start to
recognize these familiar elements these
familiar shapes in music it makes
learning new songs and pieces much
easier and clearer and quicker anyway
when i say basic chords i really mean
major and minor chords which are three
note chords and they're the most common
ones we use now there's other chords too
but they're the most useful ones to
focus on first and they can kind of act
like a framework and a foundation to
help you learn more chords in the future
recognize new shapes and inversion
positions then simply put adjust those
same chords just with the notes
rearranged in another order and they're
just common ways that we play those
chords there's videos below to help you
learn and memorize all those chords and
inversions in a way that's most
practically useful for you there's
guided practice videos to help test you
and there's pdfs on those too with
helpful theory stuff and big glossaries
of chords
theory does not have to be complicated
in fact when you learn it the right way
it's a way to make things clearer and
simpler and in a very practical way it
can really help you find and recognize
new chords new scales new shapes on the
piano and that's why i always teach
theory from a very practical standpoint
to really get the most out of it often
theory is really just labeling stuff
that we use a lot and when you get used
to that terminology a little bit it just
makes it much easier to learn new things
and understand what people are talking
about so in the beginning there's a few
things to do like learning to name the
notes half steps and whole steps and
then moving on to how to build chords
and build scales and numbering notes and
using something called intervals then
there's something that's really helpful
is learning the chords that fit inside a
key the chords that we can get using the
notes
from a scale
that's really helpful for learning how
songs are put together there's the
terminology we use for rhythm things
like eighth notes quarter notes and time
signatures there's some other stuff
specific to reading too and this
vocabulary is also going to help you
learn to pick music apart and how it
works and help you write music it really
does help you with so many things and
again i've got videos on that stuff
linked below
i would keep listening to lots and lots
of music music i love but try and
broaden my horizons to listen to new
things and when i say listen i mean
really listen listen actively to the
music think about what's happening in
the music because as well as keeping you
excited and motivated to learn really
listening to music can help you absorb
the language and develop musical
instincts and that kind of stuff often
comes out in how you play something and
it's the kind of thing that you can only
really get through experiencing and
listening to music especially listen to
recordings of something that you're
learning
consistency really is the key when it
comes to practice and learning piano of
course you have to learn how to practice
each thing well but to keep that
momentum going it's really important to
try and get in a routine of when you sit
down and play psychologically but also
it's really important to keep everything
that you're working on fresh and present
in your mind so that eventually you can
ingrain this stuff till it feels like
second nature till it feels easy and
that might be a section of a piece
you're working on it might be working on
scales it might be your sight reading
whatever it is i would keep practicing
often and avoid big gaps between playing
and to make that easier i would keep my
setup permanent because otherwise having
the thought of having to get everything
out is going to put you off getting
started i don't teach people how to
start learning to read and play at the
same time on day one personally i think
it's important to get some practical
experience first before learning how
that sheet music can give you the
information of what to play instead of
trying to learn two brand new quite
difficult things simultaneously but
having said that because learning to
read beyond the basics is quite a long
process to get comfortable with i would
start early on i know this isn't
everyone's goal but let me first quickly
separate reading and sight reading and i
like to treat them as different
practices first i would just start
learning the basics of how sheet music
works how you can figure out something
from the page all the rhythms and the
notes and everything once you get those
basics it just gives you another option
for learning new material a new
vocabulary to learn from not all kinds
of music is best to learn from a sheet
but some of it is particularly classical
stuff and learning how to read sheet
music gives you much easier access to it
secondly then after a while i'm going to
focus on sight reading and by that i
mean being able to look at something and
basically play it straight away so for
that i'm going to use far more simple
exercises we can learn our main pieces
by figuring it out slowly and piecing it
together from sheet music and then work
on much simpler stuff that you're
practicing reading and playing at the
same time straight away i haven't really
covered reading stuff so much on the
channel yet but there will be some more
videos coming up
something that i feel does often get
overlooked in more traditional piano
education is the importance of training
your ears your ears as a musician are
your greatest asset and they kind of
guide everything that you do as well as
paying attention to your own playing
really listening to what you're doing
and developing a good sense of awareness
for the details and the nuance it's
really important early on to try and
develop a connection to the sounds in
music and it really does help you learn
much more effectively it doesn't need to
be complicated to start with i want to
do some training videos on the channel
but even at the beginning important
things are just being able to match a
pitch harm a note hum a melody
practicing copying figuring out very
simple melodies on the piano and really
just getting used to how notes move up
and down often inside a major scale or a
minor scale and then further down the
road we can learn to hear how different
chords sound how different scales sound
and learning to hear intervals hearing
which note of the scale we're on as well
is a little bit more advanced um but a
really fun and musical way to get this
stuff more naturally is to practice some
simple improvisation improv as well as
just experimenting trying to come up
with stuff trying to write your own
music is a really good way to get your
ears more tuned into music
okay i won't hop on about this one so
much because i know most of you are here
because you're learning by yourself i've
learned i've had teachers but i've
learned a hell of a lot by myself as
well regular lessons can really help you
get a structure in your learning and
make you accountable i suppose to
practice but they are really expensive
what is another good option though is if
you can find a teacher that's happy to
do occasional one-off lessons not all
teachers will do this but some do and
even with just an occasional session you
can get that feedback specific to you
specific to your needs and it might
identify problems that you didn't
realize you were having specifically
technical ones a teacher may point
something out that you didn't think to
ask or didn't know to look for that
might be a real game changer for you as
great as youtube is channels like mine
well i'm always trying to cover things
that i know that the vast majority of
people are going to need whether they
realize that they need it or not but the
problem with channels like mine is that
we have to cater to lots of people but
if you can it's going to be really
helpful to get the odd lesson that's
specifically tailored for you
i would do some dedicated run-throughs
of whatever it is where i'm specifically
focused on playing the rhythm really
accurately over the years i've become
more and more aware of how important the
rhythm is especially with simple things
actually to making it sound good i'm
going to do some how to improve your
rhythm videos really soon but a couple
of things like obviously using a
metronome i've been using this vibrating
one recently which is really helpful i
think it'd be helpful for beginners i
know it can be tricky to start using a
metronome but it's really important so i
want to try and do a video on that as
well soon to help you and even if you're
not wanting to learn to read just
learning how to read rhythm i think
would be really helpful for you because
it's going to help you kind of visualize
how rhythm works and we use that kind of
terminology whether you're reading or
not so always have some run-throughs of
what you're learning where you're
specifically focused on nailing the
rhythm
i would try and get good at actually
practicing learning good practice
methods and be able to make the best use
of my time at the piano when you're
learning by yourself you have to be your
own teacher and i could make a whole
series of videos on this but i want to
give you a few important things in this
video for beginners mindful practice is
really important so that when you're
having a run through of something you
know exactly what you're working on when
you're doing it so to start with it
might just be trying to memorize the
notes it might be working on the
fingering the next time it might be
honing the rhythm or it may be a
specific element of your technique
you're trying to work on try and have
specific goals for each run-through of
exercises you're learning or pieces
you're working on don't play or don't
practice too fast there's often just too
much going on to keep up with in the
beginning stages and it doesn't help you
learn anything in general it's much
better and clearer to learn things
slowly learn to piece it together and
then speed it up so you need to go slow
to give yourself that thinking time to
process everything you have to do and
always be aware of your technique pay
attention to what you're doing what you
could do differently and how that's
going to help you move around and play
something more efficiently technique
can't really be neglected because it's
what gives you the control and the
freedom to actually make something sound
musical i've just tried to sum those
things up quite quickly there but i do
talk about that stuff a lot on the
channel
and lastly i would try and find a really
good pool of resources to help me learn
if you can find some kind of structure
to help you learn that's going to be
helpful for a lot of people i know a lot
of people use this alfred method book
i'll put a link for that below i did a
review of it ages ago too i know a lot
of people use courses and apps and
things these days now i haven't actually
really investigated them enough myself
so it wouldn't feel right to give a
recommendation my instinct tells me that
they must be useful for some people to
give them a progression to work through
and keep them playing but i'm not sure
what the actual contents like without
trying it out properly but if you've
ever used one let me know below in the
comments what you thought i can't
imagine that any of them are all
encompassing so obviously youtube is a
fantastic place to learn from there's
lots of really good channels i'm sure
you guys already watched some of the
bigger channels i'm going to put some
links below to some other channels which
i think are really useful but i will
mention one quickly in the video which
is a smaller channel like mine called
pianolab which i think will be really
helpful for you guys and the main focus
of that channel is really technique
based and how to overcome specific
technical problems and play without
tension speaking of tension you should
watch this video next which is going to
help you lift up and move around the
piano with a nice relaxed wrist which is
going to help you play everything much
easier thanks for watching